hello and
welcome it is April 29th 2024 we're in
active guest stream
82.1 with Robert Warden discussing
basian modelbased cognition the
requirement equation thank you Robert to
you for introduction and jumping into a
presentation and discussion thanks for
joining
hi I'm Robert Wen and I work theoretical
neurobiology group at UCL London um I'm
going to talk in this live stream about
an equation called the requirement
equation which has a lot to do with free
energy principle and and active
inference but it's not the same thing um
and I hope this is the first of a series
of live streams talking about how we
apply these ideas to 3D spatial
cognition
particularly and eventually to conscious
but to get on with this presentation
here's a summary of the key
ideas the main idea of this requirement
equation is to ask not ask what brains
have to do not ask how they do it and so
this approach is different from the free
energy principle and active inference
but I believe it complements it in a way
I'll try to
explain so as a statement of what brains
have to do there is this requirement
equation
which is a mathematical
equation essentially brains need to
compute it or to give the same answer as
if they computed it to give the greatest
possible Fitness to their owners so
that's it's a statement of what brains
need to do and it's not a statement of
how they need to do it doesn't say
anything about neurons or pre- energy
minimalization or anything like that it
simply says to get as fit as possible a
brain has to do this and I'll describe
what this is and it turns out this
requirement equation is like bases
theorem it's very similar to Bases
theorem but it has some extra terms in
it and you'll see that and because it's
the fittest possible brain brains have
to evolve towards the requirement
equation towards doing that thing and
the trouble is the requirement equation
itself is too expensive to compute and
brains don't compute it so um animals
don't compute it but they have to
produce very similar results to that but
we can compute the requirement equation
we can compute it by brute force and
this makes no assumptions about how
brains do it and so that gives the best
possible Fitness that's a kind of yard
stick against which you can calibrate
any model of
cognition and in particularly you can
use it to calibrate and Test free Fe and
active inference models and I'll will
put the Viewpoint that they are really
approxim to this equation and so we can
test active inference models by
comparing their results with the
requirement equation results so the
first part of this talk is to derive
this equation and show you how it works
the second part of the talk is to show
how it can be used to test and
calibrate active inference models and
the third part in point six is just a
few remarks about internal basian
models Okay so
to start how do we characterize what a
brain does without making assumptions
about how it does it and the first
characterization is a black box that
takes sense data as it
inputs and produces choices of actions
as its output so that's all a brain does
takes a set of sense data D which can
include Vision touch all sorts of stuff
and then it chooses an
action now we want to go a little bit
beyond that Black Box model and we're
going to what I call a a gray box model
shown in the lower diagram and what
happens is this the brain examines it
has a set of possible actions AI I is 1
two 3 Etc now for each of those possible
actions it calculates some real function
f of d and a and that real function
depends on both the sense data and the
action it's going to choose so f is a
kind of expected payoff for that action
in these
circumstances and then the brain
Compares all the possible FS so here we
are on the bottom left diagram it's
Computing a bunch of different Fs in
parallel and then it puts them all to
comparison and it picks the biggest one
it picks the best possible payoff from
uh any
action and so this is a gray box model
it's it's assuming the brain looks at
all the Alternatives and chooses the
best one but it doesn't assume more than
that it doesn't assume how it computes
the fs or what the fs are it just
assumes that it Compares them all and
picks the best one so that's kind of
minimal set of assumptions about how a
brain
works now we'll go on to put that set of
assumptions
inside a real life situation where we've
got probabilities and this comes in the
next
diagram this is a kind of meta model of
how brains work work life for an animal
is divided number of different domains
where it has different kinds of decision
to make and it has Encounters in each
domain and we show here a picture of one
encounter in one domain so we start on
the left there is s which is a state of
affairs that's a state of the world and
it has a certain probability a prior
probability P of s and the animal
doesn't know what that state is of
course but the state gives rise to sense
data in the animal so these two arrows
here show sense data about the external
world and sense data about the animal's
internal state so the animal has some
sense data D which it receives with a
conditional probability for any given
State s it gets sense data D with a
conditional probability P of D given s
then it has a decision function f that I
talked about in the previous slide and
it computes f of DNA for all the
possible A's it might think of uh of
doing
and then it chooses one of the actions a
and what happens when it chooses an
action is the action a and the previous
state s lead to a next state which are
called S
Prime and so that comes about with a
certain conditional probability again P
of S Prime given s and a and that next
state has a certain value to the
animal and that value relates in some
way to its lifetime fitness and so
that's in principle the computation and
the assumption is the brains act as if
they've computed F ofda to choose their
actions and this as if will turn out to
be very important so how do we use these
probabilities in terms of an actual
situation the mean payoff an animal has
loads of different Encounters in its
life and the mean payoff is just given
by this expression and so W is the
average over all the states of Affairs
he going to encounter weed by their
probabilities and then each state of
affairs gives it some sense data D with
a certain probability so it gets all the
possible sense sta that it might have
then it makes a decision chooses an
action AF ofd and that
produces a new state S Prime with a
probability P of S Prime given s and a
of D and there's a value for the new
state value for the animal of a new
state for instance if it's dead the
value is zero and so on so this is just
a straight application of probabilities
the previous diagram and you get that
formula and
um then you just rearrange the formula
slightly what you do is you shove this
first term PS inside the second term and
then you write it this way W is a sum of
functions J of D and J of D is this
thing and it's already beginning to look
very like bases here you can see but
it's got some extra stuff at the end
it's got these values stuck in at the
end
so that is the first step towards the
this requirement equation and to
understand how it's used what I'm going
to do is to choose a very simple example
of an
animal um a simple special case and the
simple special case come out here is an
animal that has only two actions and I
think you can imagine something like a
clam living in the sea it has two
actions it can open up and try and eat
consume food or it can shut down it can
clam up and so those two actions are
called action one and action two and
this simple animal has very little sense
St it only has one piece of sense data
it can say detect the cinity of the
water or the temperature of the water
and that thing it can detect with it
sense state
has values between n and one and now we
consider various kinds of this simple
animal firstly we consider two
no-brainer animals a no-brainer is an
animal that doesn't use its sense data
and just makes the same choice of
actions the whole time
and
so the animal that is open all the time
it gets value H1 of D and depending on D
it gets a pay off positive less positive
more positive and so on an
animal that stays closed all the time
gets a payoff H2 of G and so you can you
can see that for each of these two
no-brain animals the average payoff is
just the
integral of P of D * h of D over this
interval not to one so that's the payoff
for a no-brain animals either W1 or
W2 but an animal can do do better than
that if it uses it sense data to choose
which action to take so a brainy animal
can choose the correct H that gives a
bigger payoff in in terms of any sense
State D so a brain animal can ride the
top of this curve it can go down here
along the green curve along the red
curve and finally along the green curve
now that gives the greatest possible
payoff the greatest possible average
uh payoff in all situations so it's the
the greatest possible
Fitness so a brain animal that can
compute these two functions H1 and H2
and can always choose the largest one is
going to get the best possible Fitness
and if it gets it wrong if it's got some
inaccuracy in the way it commutes H1 or
H2 so these overlap points move around a
little it gets less average
fitness uh quadratically away from that
best point so that's what happens in a
very simple case where you got two
actions and one real piece of sense
data now we're going to generalize back
again and you can see what kind of
decision function this simple animal's
got to make the decision function it's
got to calculate is basically the
average fitness uh and and that gives it
the greatest possible Fitness over all
situations so if we generalize away from
this to the more General case can you
see all that slide I hope you can yes um
so we generalize this case to when the
anals got more choices of action say
five actions or an infinite number of
actions and more sense data different
dimensions of sense data and you can see
then you generalize away from the simple
case to the general case that the best
possible decision function is given by
this equation the decision function f is
the sum over all states of the probity
of the State uh weighted by the
posterior probability and the sum
overall final states of the probability
of the final State weighted by the value
of that final State and we could
simplify that by this equation but that
equation is basically a definition which
doesn't say anything about what happens
inside a brain how it computes it it
says if a brain chooses the same actions
as if it had work at these equations it
gets the best possible Fitness so the
requirement equation which is is here
says what brains are required to do and
any brain which chooses actions as if it
had done all this has the best possible
Fitness so that means that brains will
evolve to choose actions as if they
computed this equation which you can see
is very like baz's theorem and so that's
the first result that comes out of this
work is that
the basian cognition the assumption that
animals use basian cognition is not
really a hypothesis I believe Carl
friston has said has been quoted as
saying that is a hypothesis this result
implies it not really a hypothesis it
follows from a piece of analysis that
makes no assumptions about how brains do
what they
do so
um I should say this derivation of the
requirement equation has some
similarities to partially observable
markof decision processes and some
differences you'll have to look at the
paper to find out those so that if you
like is the end of the first part of the
talk which is deriving this
equation and uh saying that is a way of
analyzing what any brain is needed to do
the second part of the talk is how you
use this
equation
so all terms that you put in the
requirement equation all those
probabilities
depend on things happening outside the
brain they depend on states of Affairs
in in the environment they depend on
sense data they depend on what's the
payoff what's what happens to the animal
after it takes various actions so it's
all external
biology and you don't have to make
assumptions about what's going on in the
brain to compute it that I think is a
big
Advantage now we can write down the
requirement equation in lots of
different domains and to do that we have
to model biology which we can observe
directly rather than modeling brains
which we can't observe very well the
trouble is Computing this requirement
equation is very expensive it's
expensive in four different ways because
to really compute it you have to sum
over all possible States s you have to
do the parallel computation over all
possible actions
a you have to sum over all possible
subsequent States S Prime and in some
domains you have to to compute the value
you have to have branching look ahead to
different future situations so it's very
expensive and
it's not tractable in animal brains they
it would be too slow to try and too
expensive to compute so animal brains
don't compute this equation they do much
cheaper as if
calculations now having said that
animals don't compute it we can compute
it because we have digital computers and
we can do the Monte Carlo Integrations
and we do the optimizations and so on to
do all of this by brute force and that's
what I will call Brute Force basan
computation and that we can compute it
it acts as a kind of yard stick which we
can use to compare actual animal
behavior how well they compute their
choices of action and any cognitive
model including models built in active
entrance so um that I I'll skip over
this slide just to say you can apply
this equation in all sorts of domains
skip right so coming on to active
inference Fe and AI models are not like
the requirement equation in that they do
make assumptions about what happens in
brains they assume there's a generative
model which is a simplified version of
the actual generative process some
simplification that the animal uses in
his brain they use variational model
fitting they minimize a variational free
energy minimize a k k Divergence between
that and minimizing a k Divergence is
the process and they have a certain
model of the fitness payoffs of actions
and they are represented as bias prior
probabilities and the animal has a goal
to minimize its surprise
and an active
inference um it predicts how animals
make the tradeoff between exploration
trying to get sense data to uh help
better future decisions and exploitation
here and now so there's a whole load of
assumptions in there which are different
from the requirement equation and so for
any Fe or active inference model we can
test those assumptions against the
requirement equation and this procedure
to do that is is here you first compute
the F AR model which you've been doing
already
anyway and you define the equivalent
requirement equation and so you make
biological assumptions about the states
in the environment about the sense data
about the consequences of actions and so
on and then you compute the requirement
equation and that as I said you can do
by Brute Force integration and
optimization and then you compare the
two sets of results requirement equation
and Fe results you compare them in terms
of the Lifetime Fitness how many
encounters of this kind does an animal
have in his lifetime how much does the
fitness vary between the
two and you get a fitness gap between
the requirement equation and the
F uh result and the requirement equation
is in some sense bound to come out
fitter and so there'll be a gap and if
that Gap is significant even a very
small Gap
1% natural selection will have improved
on the Fe model in other words if
there's a 1% difference in Fitness
between two animals in a 100 Generations
the fitter animal come to dominate the
population and based on that you can use
you can refine the FP model in other
words you can ask questions like what's
the sense data which makes the largest
Fitness Gap what can we do to
get the FP model better for th those
kinds of sense data so I'll illustrate
this process
here
um some animal has a Lifetime Fitness
which you measure percentages we compute
what that is in the requirement equation
so that's that point there we also
compute what it is in the Fe and those
are
different um and we can also by the way
look at Nob brainer animals we just make
same super decision every time or real
animals all four points on this C graph
can be computed and the interesting
comparison is here between the Fe active
inference and the requirement equation
so the question we're asking is how
close is the F model to the
optimum
and what is the gap between the two and
what difference is that going to make
over say 100 generations of natural
selection now I think this comparing
with the requirement equation is a very
useful thing to do for an Fe and AI
models it's a win-win test if the model
comes very close to the optimum then
you've confirmed it can't do better than
that but if it's not very close you can
work out how to improve it you work out
what sense data is not doing so well for
how to make it do better for those sense
data right um
now we come on to the third part of the
talk and the headline is that brains are
not always basian I know
uh it's it has been stated an assumption
that brains are basian the requirement
equation tells you exactly what are the
circumstances under which they are
basian and under what circumstances they
don't don't need to be
basian and it turns out that in complex
domains where there are complicated
choic of actions the brain needs to
build an internal model and the two most
complex domains in that respect are
two-dimensional navigation finding a way
around and 3D spatial
cognition and there's always been a kind
of debate between in modeling people and
in
activist people who say the brain just
reacts to events you can prove this way
that in complex domains an inactivist
brain may do a job but it doesn't do as
good a job as a brain that makes an
internal model and
so you can prove in certain domains main
of the complicated ones that you need to
build internal models you can't build
that prove that in all domains in simple
domains models aren't needed and these
are domains in which there are very few
choices of action or very simple States
or simple sense data and in these simple
domains the as if
computation can be uh very simple it can
just be a matter of um some very simple
neural relay and no internal model is
needed and an example of that is a
special case that I use to motivate the
requirement equation where you've only
got two possible
actions you don't have to build a
complete internal model of what's going
on you simply have to know the
thresholds at which you switch from one
action to the other and this can be seen
in terms of information
capacity what comes into the brain is
some basium priers which have made it
evolve and some sense data and it makes
an internal model or may or may not make
an internal model and then it chooses
actions now if the choice of action is
very small it's very small information
content then it doesn't need to make a
big complicated internal model in order
to make that simple choice so the
information in the internal
model needs to be less than the
information in the choice of actions and
if the choice of actions is very simple
small information content there is no
point in constructing a very complicated
internal model it's a waste of uh
effort so if you regard the brain's
internal models as an informational
Channel between sense State and actions
then you can see the information model
is very necessary in complex domains but
not so necessary in simple domains now
now as a further comment on this
um I say you should not trust the good
regulator theorem now in Fe literature
the good regulat theorem is often cited
as support for the idea that brains need
internal models I'll just very briefly
say I don't believe it does give good
support when you compare it with the
requirement meta model and the good
regulator theorem which was paper in
1970 by con Ashby that has a couple of
different metamodels of what cognition
is about and it's based on Ash's ideas
of
homeostasis but I think the argument
they make Con Ashby make from the good
regulator theorem I don't think it
really holds up and I've just listed the
reasons here um there's the good
regulator result every good regulator of
the system is a model of that system
here's the requirement equation result
in complex domains only the fittest
brains canut a model of the
domain now the regulator model I'll
assert is not a realistic model it lacks
some key
ingredient and uh it's less realistic it
assumes a homeostatic picture of a
brain where the requirement equation
analysis is much more flexible and
realistic but mainly this fourth point
the regulator concept of a model is not
a graduate ated it's a yes no All or
Nothing
concept and what it
says is a model how they Define a model
you can have any function of the system
variables can be a model of the system
even a very trivial
function and so the concept of model
they use is a binary yes no concept but
the real meaning of you of model in
everyday life and in science is a
graduated in other words the more
complicated the more detail there is in
a model the more it counts as a model so
um this is just my personal uh beef you
should not be using the good and
regulator theorem to justify internal
models a few remarks about how brains
evolve because obviously this
analysis depends totally on the idea
that the requirement equation defines
the fittest possible brain and brains
evolve towards that
Optimum and as I said even a small
deficit in Lifetime Fitness even a 1%
deficit in Lifetime Fitness over a 100
Generations that gives enough selection
pressure to make something start
dominating the
population but if the probabilities in
the habitat change rapidly brains can't
catch up they only evolve very slowly by
random
mutations and therefore if the
properties in the habitat are changing
brains need to learn and they need to
learn fast within a short animal
Lifetime and you can actually apply this
requirement equation analysis to
learning and animal learning it turns
out is very close to the kind of
learning you get out of the requirement
equation on the other hand if
probabilities in the habitat stay
constant for very long time brains can
evolve to come very close to the optimum
and the key
place where this is the case is spatial
cognition 3D spatial
cognition where the states of the world
have to obey some very strong
constraints they have to obey ukian
geometry and they obey constraints of
physics and these constraints have been
true for all EV evolutionary time so
animal brains have evolved to embody
those constraints very
precisely uh a final point is that
animals we know have very precise and
sensitive sense organs they would not
have evolved if the brain couldn't make
the very best use of the data from
them so here's a plug for the next live
stream the next live stream is applying
these ideas to 3D spatial
cognition understanding
three-dimensional local space is
actually the most important thing a
brain can do because it has very huge
impact on Survival because it's a 3D
model of local space is used to control
physical movements at every moment in
the day and if the model is as
inaccurate mistakes in movement can cost
the animal's life any time and they're
also used for recognizing things and
action so the selection pressure to get
the internal model of 3D space good has
been very strong and sustained over 500
million years since the camera in
explosion When Animals first had Limbs
and precise sense
data even insects control their
movements very
well and Consciousness shows that our
own internal human internal model of
space is a good precise model so the 3D
model of space is a very good
model and what this next live stream is
going to talk about is how you build
that how you build neural models of 3D
local space now people have there have
been very few attempts to do this there
are no
working neural models of 3D spatial
cognition that I know about one of the
reasons is the architecture because how
do you what's the neural architecture to
represent three dimensions of
space neural sheets can represent
two-dimensional space but there's no
equivalent Arch architecture for
3D and the key problem is neural spatial
memory if you represent spatial
coordinates by neuron firing rates it
turns out that that memory is too
imprecise and too slow insects for
instance have a tiny fraction of a
second to work out what their
surroundings are like and in that space
of time you can't get precise
representation of 3D space using neuron
firing so in the next live stream I will
introduce the proposal that 3D space is
not represented by neuron firing at all
but it's represented by a wave in the
brain and that wave is actually a
projective transform of 3D space and
that's the same Transformers used in in
the projective Consciousness model PCM
which is an Fe derived model of
Consciousness so that's the commercial
for the next uh live stream just to
summarize on this live
stream gosh I've been quick 30 minutes
um there are two kinds of modeling you
can do you can model by biology or you
can model the
brain and modeling biology is a great
deal easier because we can observe it we
can observe easily uh what's happening
to animals in their habitat whereas
modeling what happens inside the brain
is more difficult there's much more
hypothesis and guesswork about it and
the requirement equation approach which
I've talked about in this talk only
requires modeling biology only need to
model events outside the brain and you
can compute this requirement equation in
any domain you like and it defines the
very best A Brain can do so it's a kind
of yard stick against which you compare
actual brains and models of
brains so you can compare the
requirement equation with any active
inference model and that I say is a
win-win for the model because if the
model comes close to the optimum then
you've confirmed it but if it doesn't
come close you can use what you learn to
work out how to improve it and I would
offer to work with anybody who wants to
make that kind of comparison with their
active INF
models okay so I finished rather ahead
of time
um
questions thank you
Robert all
right thank you for the presentation
there's a lot to discuss and also people
can write question questions in live
chat while I'm just like recro
everything um do you want to give any
like context how did you come to study
this question and how did you get to
this equation and
why
um I got to this equation about 25 years
ago actually um and I came back to it
when I joined Carl's group and got
interested in requirements in Fe and so
on and I realized there was a link
between it and and Fe and active
inference and I've just been working
recently to work out what the link is
and this is what I think the link is um
but I think it's a a very basic
foundation for studying the brain is to
not make hypothesis about what is how
brains do what they do but to just
analyze what they have to do and I think
this is quite a powerful approach in all
sorts of
domains hope to convert one to people
to yeah okay while questions are kind of
coming in I'll go over a few of my notes
just to go over some of these core
pieces because I think there's a lot lot
to say and it's really exciting um in
quantitative evolutionary population
biology Fitness is conceived of as like
a top down
Force whereas the generative model is
built up as like an agent level view
from the inside like agent based
modeling with kind of a top down
pressure and and that's one uh way to
look at that kind of setting and I got
the sense that I I want to explore and
learn more about that the requirements
equation sits basically between those
two and sets the high bar that gives a
requirements for the agent-based model
because you can always just build an
agent based model than have a
constraining force we know from
simulations that that all does give um
Improvement of
algorithms uh in
simulations but it's kind of an
open-ended search and there isn't
necessarily A
calibration what do you think about this
is a calibration yeah if if you are
prepared
to analyze an animal's lifetime in terms
of number of different
encounters like each time it goes out to
get food or each time it meets a
potential mate or each time it comes
across a predator and say what's his
probability of surviving all those
encounters then you can start doing the
requirement equation analysis and you
can find in principle you can find the
very best it can do and that is an
endpoint if you if you got your FP model
and you're improving it improving it
this is a kind of end point Beyond which
you don't expect to get but you know
when you're getting
near awesome and here's one other kind
of angle that I was noting so the
Standalone Baye
equation Baye with no additional terms
is like this unified imperative for
sense making it can cover discrete or
continuous State spaces single Dimension
multiple Dimensions there's even
considerations for like how many
parameters should be Bay optimal but
it's it's all framed in terms of this um
unified sense making imperative the
requirements equation and and so then
one of the key steps in active inference
is to expand that unified basian
imperative to not just the sensemaking
but include action like a variational
autoencoder with action the requirements
equation says well it's a a little bit
more over the lifespan than just optimal
sense making about about sense and
action action but not sense making has
Fitness or survival
consequences so then there's another
term that applies to only actions
because there's a direct Fitness
consequence of actions and
phenotypes whereas the internal sense
making is actually shielded from direct
selection because it has no consequence
except through the actions in the black
or the gray
box yeah I mean I I think active
inference is a particular way of making
the tradeoff between I mean the way I
understand it it's a bit simple the
trade-off between exploration and
exploitation in other words do I fly
higher so I can see more prey or do I go
down and actually catch that bit of prey
and the requirement equation can
Encompass that because the value that an
animal gets from an
action can be direct exploitation that
gets a piece of food or it can be
exploration that it learns something
that it can use Downstream so that kind
of tradeoff is made in active inference
there is also the the apparatus in the
requirement equations we making the same
tradeoff and see if you get the same
answers Just One Last Framing and then
I'll go to the live chat questions just
at the purely empirical even just
putting aside The evolutionary setting
it's a common theme to make a model and
then do a variance partitioning on the
residual and find if it's loaded or
associated with anything so when we're
studying bird migration and empirically
80% survive some stage and then we're
making an agent based model well we
don't want a model where 100% of them
survive because that we've kind of
overshot how successful so then the
empirical path could be like okay we
just made a simple version and it 50% of
the simulated birds make the
migration how is that correlated with
the actual and then how is the what's
left in the residual oh It's associated
with age okay now we include age as a
factor in the agent based model that
eats up some of that variance how is the
remaining variance associated with known
or unknown factors and so there's an
iterative
process where you can discover
potentially Associated
variables and have that in feedback with
the agent based constructions like the
agent responds to requirements as
modeled and then it looks like they're
doing something else that's required
that you don't have in your requirements
equation so then but it sets a kind of
local calibrator again
to what kind of performance envelope
could even be expected or relevant so
that you don't have in silico
experiments where like bacteria are
trying to read a book and a person is
trying to do a metabolic thing that they
can't do it doesn't make sense we all
have a feeling like well that's not the
niche it's not what they are being
selected on for and so this again helps
put an adapter in between the kind of
bulk properties of the niche and then
the specific
performance that gets all the way down
to thinking like you mentioned about
like the survival through time as being
like the joint distribution of many many
many many many
encounters yeah I mean I I agree with
all that I I think the requirement
equation can be used to do those kinds
of analysis when when you when you
formulate it you're really looking at
Lifetime Fitness and so you should be
looking at all the things that influence
Lifetime Fitness including things that
are nothing to do with brains at all as
you say old age whatever but
nevertheless the requirement equation it
gives you I I
think starting just from FP models and
AI models you have the model on the one
hand
and practical observational animals on
the on the other hand and you've got
nothing in between but requirement
equation is some in between them that
you can say here's this requirement for
what a brain needs to do and if a brain
does it absolutely as well as that then
here's the survival so you got a
midpoint in the calibration between your
brain model and your real
life
awesome okay I'm going to go to read
some questions in the chat if whatever
you want to say or answer or well just
however you see okay B asks is an
activism exclusive to internal
representations I always think of it
that way an activism is generally the
idea that you don't need internal
representations you can just sort of do
something um and in simple cases you can
in that simple clam case the clam case
only has to know what are the three
thresholds at which he has to switch
over from open to closed that's an
active IST I think an activist is
usually hostile to internal
representations and they are in
opposition and what I'm saying is the
requirement equation tells you which
circumstances one is right and which
circumstances the other is
Right awesome one other free energy
principle paper that this reminded me of
and then I'll go back to the live chats
was by yela brunberg in and others in
2018 the anticipating brain is not a
scientist the free energy principle from
an ecological inactive perspective which
discusses it's kind of like the good
scientist and the good engineer like
it's not just the pure sense making
imperative when action is considered
it's not just about accuracy and action
because actions have consequences in a
way that the sense making component
doesn't because the black or the gray
box is set up so that the sensemaking
doesn't have consequences except through
action that's that partitioning if you
explored a model with telepathy where
there was direct consequence for
internal States then it would be
basically as if that was an external or
an action State because it would just
make those yeah representations external
facing so it's like whichever States
aren't external facing are the internal
ones whichever ones are external facing
and then those can be under quote no
selective pressure if they're all all
that's like a novelty type or just an
open diffusion space or it can be under
strong selection pressure which just
means that there are higher consequences
for a certain distribution but that's a
distribution that you're actually having
the agent model converge towards and
maybe it NE maybe the population convert
maybe the optimal height would be like
15 ft and it just there's so many other
trade-offs that that actually the
population just continues to push up
against five but at least there was a
way to say well it only got to a third
of the value but that's the highest
score is
30% yeah and that sort of approach
sounds very congenial to what I'm doing
I have to read the paper I'm afraid I
haven't read it yet but certainly will
do okay all right Benjamin
asks how does the amalgamation of
maravian Dynamics and basian Theory
reflect the necessity for brains in
complex domains to construct internal
models for better adaptation and decis
decision
making how does the combination
of marov
Dynamics yeah how how does how you
brought together I think this equation
you're good sorry um this equation
certainly builds in maravian Dynamics I
mean the probabilistic model of the
states is a maravian model if there are
certain State transitions in the
world then those are modeled so
I um I believe that that's encompassing
this approach I don't know the word
maravian changes things
particularly
okay Benjamin asked another
question as the brain has evolved do we
know which of these definitions of brain
functions are inherent versus emergent
and how does this potentially impact
their functioning as they evolve
collaboratively or indep
dependently um seem to be two questions
there can you read it again yes oh we
have many amazing um conjugate question
askers um how do we know which of the
definitions of brain functions are
inherent versus emergence I think that's
the first part inherent versus emergent
right and then how does that impact
their functioning as they evolve
potentially collaboratively or
independent
L well the requirement I've tried to
State the
requirement um in know words what brains
are required to do
as in the abstract and making no mention
of how they've actually evolved to do it
and that applies to brains at the very
beginning of their evolution when they
were totally unfit um and they gradually
got fitter by natural selection so
inherent versus emergent I mean what
what is emergent is brains getting
closer and closer to an Optimum given by
that equation the equation doesn't
describe how brains are it describes
where brains are evolving
towards so that's the first part of the
question now the second part of the
question was a different
contrast which was how does that
potentially impact their functioning as
they evolve collaboratively
independently now collaboratively or
independently there's a huge amount of
question there I mean obviously um
social insects for instance uh their
brains work
collaboratively is that the distinction
we're talking about I mean again I think
the requirement equation is applicable
to social insects that don't have
they're not so concerned about
individual survival they're uh concerned
about survival of the genotype of the
hive if if you like but I think the
equation still applies to that but
collaboration and competition are very
complicated areas to
analyze well definitely especially next
time I look forward to going very deep
into the insect questions um I'll I'll
give some thoughts though I mean to the
first half in inherent versus
emergent without just saying it depends
on how you define
it it can be emergent through
development that certain
functions arise so that that can be both
inherent feature that was the sense of
the question was it emergent in a
lifetime I don't know what the sense of
the question was maybe I didn't get that
right certainly
um emerging in a lifetime yeah um
because
it's optimizing Lifetime Fitness you
have to consider different periods in
the lifetime and whether the brain gets
fit in adulthood by having leared along
the way or having
inherent um innate
traits uh is a choice that brains have
but
um uh as I said the requirement equation
can be applied to learning and that's a
very interesting application I haven't
done talked about it at all here but it
can be and there's a result a book from
Anderson in
1990 which shows that data on annual
condition the sort of rats and pigeons
in cages and so on um agrees very well
with the basian model the requirement
equation model of how what the best
possible learning is so that's um
another domain in which um the Basin
assumptions are
confirmed interesting this is making me
wonder about abiotic constraints and
biotic constraints for the requirements
equation so maybe one setting is that
the external environment of the organism
is very harsh like it's a desert ants
colony and so a lot of the selective
pressure and the differences amongst
colonies like in their persistence or
their survival is related to their
performance against the environment and
there's another setting where maybe the
environment is materially abund but then
there's a lot
of Dynamics like Game Theory and sexual
selection and like these internal so how
how does the requirements equation I
mean if we have to change that as often
as the weather changes then what are we
really getting by just setting this
local requirement which itself could be
changing all the time or variable across
settings that's a great question I mean
in principle the requirement equation
takes as its starting point natural
selection not sexual selection because
sexual selection as you know doesn't
make animals doesn't always make animals
fitter and sometimes makes them less fit
as in the peacock's tail and I've got a
whole separate interest in how sexual
selection has acted on the human brain
particularly and in terms of Social and
sexual
competition um and that I
think the requirement equation is not
not a result of that requirement
equation is what you get after natural
selection what do you mean after natural
selection well natural selection
uh you have to have the fittest possible
the fittest possible animal is one that
survives to adulter with the greatest
probability and gets a mate with the
greatest
probability getting a mate with the
probability is not as simple as
surviving with the greatest probability
because it's a competitive
activity and you get positive feedback
effects for
instance as in the classic Peacock case
where female peacocks prefer males with
long tails and uh and and so that gets
baked into the genotype by a kind of
conspiracy between fem female genes
preferring longtails and male genes
having long tails but it's not good for
the peacock species in terms of Fitness
male PE peacocks are less fit because
they got big tails and you could have
similar things like that happening
inside the brain and I have all separate
uh set of ideas which I would love to
give a talk about sometime that natur
that human language is actually a
consequence of sexual
selection um perhaps we could live
stream that sometime
but human language hasn't made us more
fit in natural
habitats there's some controversy for
you
wow to return to one other potentially
interesting um aspect of of Benjamin's
question there with the second half
collaborative or
independent uh challenges so this made
me think about how the factorization of
the problem to be solved like the
sparsity of what depends on what in the
problem
may be very disjoint from what is
connected to what in the organism so
that's kind of widely been recognized by
like evolutionary constraints or just
evolutionary or tray
architectures
like yeah if there's a covariance in the
niche um between two factors and then
that is not the case in the organism
then there can be like separated
movement of those Ates or you can have
the opposite setting where two things
are I mean there's also pieces that are
correlated just like having length and
volume like having a longer body Le
other trait to
change I would guess that in terms of
physical evolution of bodies uh you can
get two traits that have to be
correlated like long legs are inevitably
correlated with something else but in
terms of evolution of the the brain it's
not so constrained and you can have
different cognitive functions that
evolve independent of each other much
much more freedom there that's just a
guess yeah that's very interesting and
the kind of there's a lot to say about
that and also with um very fruitful to
consider the differences with the mammal
nervous system and with the insect
nervous system and the ways in which the
insect nervous system
helps clarify certain sensory mappings
that get very lost in the large mamal
Brain
yeah I agree insects are very worth
looking
at
um okay so anyone else can write
questions in the live chat but I mean
what other directions would you like to
explore how how do you think this moves
forward given where it is now
well as I say I'd be very interested if
anybody's interested in taking an active
inference model and kind trying to
calibrate it this way I'd be very happy
to work with them too I would do the
requirement equation side of things and
uh that would be a very interesting
comparison for me to
make
but say we're going to make the next
live stream in in a month's time and
that's be about spatial cognition that's
the main Direction I want to take
this yes moving things animals with
spatialized nervous systems and then
also nervous systems that enable
movement but don't necessarily need to
be spatialized like a worm may just have
a
topological or tactile mapping but it
may not need to have
the kinds of echolocation or Centerplace
foraging components of a bat or a
be I agree I
agree um am I allowed to play with
Robert's equation is that
okay of course you are of course you are
okay um all right so this is very cool
it sounds like in around 1 month we will
have a session on insect brain and
forging spatial cognition and then
there's probably many other things we
can continue to talk about and also it
would be awesome if um somebody has a
active inference model or some other
kind of model that they could reach out
to you
and try to get some more empirical and
specific well has have you applied this
to any specific like empirical or
published cases yet so people could see
like what the kind of anal is
is um well the main analysis is coming
in the second live stream C can I just
uh move to the
slide that um shows where you can get
hold of the
paper
yes so there is the link to get hold of
the
papers yeah and there's an application
which we'll look at next time as well
but there's a very um
interesting video game
slash
executable
simulation Bas language you.org Bas
language.
org cool all right thank you very much
Robert thanks everyone for the comments
the questions in the chat all right okay
great thanks farewell bye
bye e